[Music]
Annie, how are you? Hello, Simon. How
are you? Hello. I'm doing well. I'm a
little bit tired, actually. I'll be
honest, but I'm doing very, very well.
It's a pleasure to chat with you again,
Annie. this time live. So, no cuts this
time, but I think we pretty much won cut
it last time anyway. So, um it's it's a
pleasure to have you back on. Um Annie
is a distinguished engineer at Westpak
New Zealand. Um and Annie, you've you've
had a a wondrous career actually. Tell
us a little bit about it. Oh, thanks
Simon. Um yeah, so I've been coding for
a long time, but I've been working as a
software engineer since I don't know
just over 20 years now. And I spent the
first half of my career as an IC, moving
between a whole bunch of different
roles, just loving it. And then
eventually reluctantly moved into
management about halfway through my
career. And and since then, I've sort of
bounced back and forward on the engineer
manager pendulum that uh charity majors
talks about and I totally recommend it
to everyone who has the opportunity to
because it it gives you great
perspective from either side.
Yeah, I've done a number of role bounces
between kind of like more IC, more
management and I totally agree. It is it
is that pendulum. I do feel that. But it
it gives it it gives you in this talk
these wonderful comparisons uh between
this kind of like move from an
individual contributor to a manager and
and the way you describe this is
absolutely wonderful. So without further
ado, let me bring your slides up and
I'll pass the mic to you. Over to you,
Annie. Great. Thank you so much, Simon.
All right. Well, thanks everyone for
having me. So my talk today is what I'm
calling the software engineer identity
crisis and and I think it's something
that many developers might start to
wonder about now that we're facing this
future where we might not be the ones to
write the code anymore. So let's get
stuck into it. Um, although Simon just
introduced me there, I I thought I might
just add that I'm a software engineer
and a technical leader, although I refer
to myself as a as a nerd and I'm very
proud to be one. And I'm currently a
distinguished engineer at Westpak, New
Zealand, but I'm also a part-time
student at the University of Oakland
where I live here in Oakland, New
Zealand, where I'm doing a masters of
engineering and I'm focusing on the
impact of AI on software
engineering. So, let's get on with it.
I thought I might kick off by explaining
a little bit about why this topic
matters so much to me. So, I've been
writing code since I was a kid. I got
this Commodore 64 when I was all six
years old and it came with both of those
basic manuals that you see in the
picture and I typed in some of the
sample code and I was absolutely hooked.
You see, there's there's something about
programming that like building things
out of thin air. It just has a really
magical feel to it. And I've loved my
career as a software engineer and I've
spent years encouraging others to
consider it as a career path themselves.
But over the last couple of years, I
kind of feel like something's been
shifting, right? Because as we celebrate
how fast we're moving and what's
possible now thanks to AI, I'm also
wondering what happens to that core of
being a software engineer. because for
some of us it could feel a little bit
like a hollowing out like we might be
losing a part of what attracted us to
the field in the first
place. So I came across this really
beautiful quote by Frederick Brooks the
author of the very famous mythical man
month and he says the programmer like
the poet works only slightly removed
from pure thought stuff. He builds his
castles in the air from air creating by
the exertion of the
imagination. Now I think it captures the
magic and power that I felt when I built
my own castles in the air by pure
thought and imagination over the years
really really
nicely because ultimately it feels so
good to build something that actually is
useful to someone anyone really that
solves a problem in a creative or
elegant way like you've made a real
difference. you know, that moment when
it it finally builds or the tests pass
and you feel that you've done it. It's a
really really nice dopamine
hit. But that's not to say that it's
always easy, right? So, in fact, quite
often it's the opposite. It's almost
always harder than it should be. And I
think many people are actually turned
off by the challenge, but for some of
us, it sort of fuels us to keep going.
Perhaps we're just suckers for
punishment. But the satisfaction of
overcoming those hurdles is huge. Even
getting your environment set up can be a
massive challenge. Let alone designing
and implementing a solution, ensuring
it's reliable and resilient, that it
scales well, it performs under load,
secure, etc.
Right? There's a lot to think about
because the reality is that software
engineering is complex and over time
we've tried to manage that complexity
through
specialization. As the demand for
software has grown and the complexity
has as well, so has our need to divide
and conquer. We've introduced product
owners to gather requirements,
architects to design solutions, quality
engineers to test them, platform
engineers to run them, security
engineers to secure it all. Well, it
goes on, right? And the result is that
in many organizations that the role of
the software engineer has narrowed
significantly, not necessarily by
accident, but by design. We gave away
the upstream and the downstream and
we've held on to the part that others
saw as uniquely ours writing the code.
Now, ironically, our industry has even
invented a new title, the product
engineer. Distinct very different to the
software engineer apparently for people
who still do all the things that
software engineers were once trusted to
do by
default. But now, generative AI is here.
The genie's out of the bottle. Pandora's
box has been opened. And guess what?
Turns out it's really, really good at
writing code. Sure, it's not perfect,
but it's so much better than many of us
ever thought would be possible. So, by
now, I'm sure, and I hope that many of
you have played with the various AI
coding assistants that are out there.
They're really quite incredible, and
they're getting better every day. My own
aha moment was watching the agentic
workflows in Windsurf kick in when I
asked it to make a change and it
recognized by itself that it had deleted
too much code. It apologized and then it
fixed it all without me having to lift a
finger. Honestly, it feels like
magic. But these tools, they're getting
so good that CEOs like Anthropic Stereo
Armaday are making statements like 90%
of the code will be written by AI in the
next 6 months. increasing to 100% of the
code shortly after that. And Mark
Zuckerberg was quoted even more recently
saying that he believes AI will soon be
better than top coders, eventually
becoming smart enough to write most of
the code by itself, probably within the
next 12 to 18 months. So, with comments
like these, it's no wonder that many
might be starting to wonder whether
there's even a role for software
engineers anymore.
There are lots of posts like these
popping up around the internet and sadly
it's often those who are thinking about
what career to choose who are
questioning whether it's too late to
start a career in software
engineering. So even if you don't
believe that software engineering is
dead, you might be starting to question
what your craft really is now. Like how
do you add value? What's your unique
skill set that you can bring to the
table you could take pride in and use to
solve real problems? Oh, and earn a good
living. These are big, almost
existential questions, right? And
they've been buzzing around in my mind
for a while. So, I wrote about
it. I wrote this blog post on the
software engineering identity crisis a
couple of months ago. And wow, I guess
I'm not the only one thinking about this
because I've had blogs on and off for a
couple of decades now. But honestly, I
generally give up because I don't think
anyone really cares what I have to say.
But this post is different. By far the
most popular blog post I've ever
written. Some might even say it went
viral. I received a bunch of feedback
from mostly total strangers thanking me
for having written it, and some even
shared their story with me. That right
there is just a little snippet of a much
longer email I got from a total stranger
who wanted to share their story and how
they're feeling about this change. And
the cherry on top, even charity majors
posted about it. Like I don't know
Charity, but I know of her. And how how
cool is that? Like if you don't know who
who Charity is, please look her up.
She's an incredible thought leader in in
technology. So you see, I've always
thought of software engineering as part
science. I mean, I did computer science
at university and loved it and part art
because designing software is a really
creative discipline. Even when we're
working within constraints, there's a
lot of room for interpretation. We each
bring our own style, thinking, and
trade-offs into the design decisions
that we make, and there's really rarely
just one right way. Other creative
disciplines have already pushed back
against AI. In early 2024, an
illustrator named Beth Spencer created
this created with human intelligence
badge as a proud celebration of
humanmade work. And she started a
movement which quickly spread across the
art community. Writers, photographers,
and voice actors, they've all rallied
too, protecting the human element of
their craft. Now, I'm not saying that
software engineers should revolt or
rally or even organize the same way, but
I think it's natural and understandable
if some of us are feeling a bit of an
emotional reaction to these
changes. Yet, despite the fears,
adoption of AI tools to help with
software development is surging. It
seems that we're a bit more ambivalent
than resistant.
So, back in 2023, GitHub ran a survey
with 500 US-based developers, of whom
92% were already using AI coding
assistance. And in 2024, Stack Overflow
surveyed nearly 61,000 developers, of
whom 62% were already using AI in their
workflows with a further 14% planning to
use it that year.
And the 2025 hacker rank developer
skills report which takes data from the
hacker rank platform and the annual
developer skills survey that they run
says that 97% of almost 13 and a half
thousand developers across the globe use
at least one AI assistant. But that
adoption and use cases do vary across
those
tools. I mean given that these tools
have only been around for a couple of
years it's it the uptake's really quite
impressive, isn't it?
Well, the thing is that the benefits of
these tools, they're pretty tempting. In
my mast's reaches research on the impact
of AI on software engineering, I ran a
survey about 7 months ago and I got
around 160 responses from professional
software engineers who are using AI and
three major themes of how AI coding
assistants are helping software
engineers emerged from a thematic
analysis of responses to open-ended
questions. So the first and most common
was time efficiency gains like obviously
faster development especially around
boilerplate code prototyping testing
generally helping us get answers
faster and there's cognitive support.
You know, many developers feel like it's
helping them try new things or
explaining complex or legacy code,
acting as a supportive pair programmer,
and in some cases starting to allow us
to focus a bit more on higher level
tasks like problem definition and system
design.
We're also seeing some improved flow
state because in many ways AI replaces
various traditional tools like Stack
Overflow, Google and documentation, and
it can help keep engineers in the IDE,
especially if they're using a plug-in or
an AI native
IDE. So, those responses to open-ended
questions also gave us some really great
insights into specific instances where
AI coding assistants are significantly
helping software engineers.
and uh I thought I might share some of
those with you. These are direct quotes
from the from the participants in my
survey. So um we saw a lot of comments
around code generation especially
boilerplate that cognitive support in
the form of a helpful coding buddy or
pair
programmer. We also see that it helps
with problem solving that technical
enablement or exploration of new
technologies.
It can help reduce that analysis
paralysis that you might feel when
you're first getting started on a new
project. And it's certainly a really
good learning aid that can help
democratize software development,
boosting confidence, and helping some
people put their hands up for roles that
they might not have otherwise.
So it's therefore really no surprise
that such a high percentage 84% of
participants in my study felt that AI
coding assistants have
significantly or at least improved their
perceived
productivity. I should note though that
the participants in my study signed up
voluntarily and as such I mean we can
assume that most of them have either
enjoyed using the tools or have some
interest in them. So there could be a
bit of bias in the data but I think we
can all agree that there are benefits
there.
So yeah, AI brings with it so many
benefits. Productivity gains in
particular, quite undisputed, and
there's plenty of research that backs
that up. But we're only just starting to
see more research on the other side of
the equation. Like what are we losing?
What are the
trade-offs? And I worry that we don't
really know yet.
So, one of the things I'm particularly
interested in understanding is which of
the software development life cycle
tasks we're spending more or less time
on because of
AI. So, as one might expect,
participants in my study reported
spending significantly less time writing
and refactoring code, as well as less
time writing tests. We also see a slight
increase in time spent reviewing code
and debugging it. potentially side
effects of being less in control of that
code and being um needing to review and
fix it a bit more
often. So, if we're spending
significantly less time writing and
refactoring code, yet we're not spending
a huge amount more time reviewing it,
are we really sure we understand what
we're building? Would we be able to
explain it if we needed to? Or do we
feel that maybe we won't need to because
AI could do that for us, too? With the
speed that AI can generate code, will we
really keep up with all the code reviews
or are we going to see a decline in
attention, otherwise known as vigilance
decrement? The truth is that while AI
smooths out the terrain for us, we may
find ourselves not even noticing what
we're stepping over anymore. And that
could have some pretty significant
consequences. This AI generally inspires
trust because it sounds so confident. It
never really signals doubt and this is a
problem because as we know it is very
non-deterministic in nature and it can
have a tendency to
hallucinate and trust in AI works quite
differently to trust between humans.
With humans we generally start off with
fairly low trust and we build it up
through positive interactions with one
another. But with AI, it generally
starts off quite high because we have
these overinflated hopes and dreams,
expectations, and the unpredictable
nature of its outputs can erode that
trust pretty
quickly. I'm not saying that AI is bad.
In fact, like I said earlier, for me, it
honestly feels like magic. But the 2025
Git Clear report which analyzed 211
million lines of code authored between
January of 2020 and December of 2024
shows that we're not just speeding up.
We may also be creating bit more of a
mess than we realize.
So they found that in 2024 alone there
was a 17.1% increase in copypasted code,
an eight-fold increase in duplicated
code blocks and a 26% increase in code
churn which is what they define as code
that has been authored, pushed to a git
repo and then reverted or substantially
revised within the subsequent two
weeks. So overall this report found
multiple signs of eroding code quality.
So, could it be that perhaps we're
trusting AI too much, too fast, often
without enough critical judgment? And
that's where calibrated trust becomes so
important. Because honestly, if this is
what productivity looks like, maybe we
need a better
definition cuz I'm quite sure that what
we want is faster and more stable
deliveries. Something which the 2024
state of DevOps report found that is
actually on the decline because of AI.
The working hypothesis is that what we
call increased productivity that
producing code faster might be part of
the problem. It seems we could be
shipping larger change sets more
quickly. And if you add to that
vigilance decrement that we just spoke
about, that tendency to pay less
attention over time, especially in tasks
like code reviews, well, we're seeing
quality take a hit. And that creates
short-term gains, but at the cost of
long-term stability, technical debt that
we may not even be noticing until it's
too
late. So, another angle that I think
about often is this. The creators of
these tools like the CEO of GitHub and
keep telling us that AI is going to free
our time up so that we can spend more
time designing highle architectures,
thinking in systems, and focusing on
intent, not syntax.
But those aren't skills that you can
just prompt into existence. They're
built over time through experience,
through deliberate practice, through
friction, frustration, and even or
perhaps more importantly,
failures. In fact, in 1980, two
brothers, Stuart and Hubert Drafus, came
up with the Drafus model of skill
acquisition to clearly articulate the
progression from novice to expert in any
given skill. They believed it takes 10
years of hard work, hard varied work to
go from novice to expert in any skill.
And with every step, you gain more
situational recollection, holistic
recognition, intuitive decision making,
and absorbed
awareness. I don't think you can just
skip these steps by writing better
prompts. And I believe that this is the
risk we face if we think we can shortcut
craftsmanship. Now the thing is that
it's not just GitHub and other AI
creators who are saying this. The World
Economic Forum agrees.
The skills that will matter most in 2023
are things like systems thinking like
the CEO of GitHub mentioned as well as
several other softer skills such as
resilience, flexibility, agility,
leadership, and social
influence. And on the other end of the
scale, the skills that they believe are
already less essential now and unlikely
to increase in use are really
fundamental ones like reading, writing,
and
maths. Oh, and programming.
Thankfully, we see that curiosity and
lifelong learning remain important
skills to harness. This really resonates
for me because I've always believed that
these are important skills to have,
especially for
engineers. So, if we start to rely too
heavily on AI generated systems without
first building our own foundation of
judgment, how will we even know if the
architecture is solid, if the
abstractions make sense, if the system
will scale? Those of us who have years
of experience in these areas are
probably okay for now, but if you've
never had to wrestle a system back under
control, how will you recognize when
things are starting to go
wrong? Technical skills take a lot of
effort and time to build up and we can
forget them pretty quickly if we don't
keep practicing and keeping up to date
with uh progress in our field. And if we
become too reliant on AI, we we let our
risk, we risk our um skills eroding and
we might end up becoming operators of
output rather than engineers of systems.
And that's why we need that calibrated
trust, learning to lean on AI when it
genuinely benefits us long term, but
also knowing when to step back, slow
down, and rely on our own judgment
instead.
So, as part of my study, I also
collected examples of how professional
software engineers perceive that AI
coding assistants are impacting their
ability to learn. And although there
were a lot of positive effects, most of
the negative ones centered around over
reliance and skill erosion. I thought
I'd share a few more of these direct
quotes from our participants with you.
So, some of us are feeling that by
building a bit of a dependency, we're no
longer remembering as much because we
tend to optimize for speed and then just
end up copying and pasting responses
without thinking it through
properly, which means that there we're
not really thinking things through
properly and and not really
understanding
it. Over reliance may also affect the
development of problem solving and
technical skills making some people
actually feel a bit dumber while others
are already trying to reduce their
dependency on it. So let's face it if we
developers like we take pride in knowing
stuff right those magical incantations
where the code has to be just right to
to do what we need it to do. We spend
years learning it, getting really good
at it, doing leak code exercises so that
we can pass some interview. And the
thought of losing those skills is really
quite
unpleasant. All of this reminds me of my
own professional identity crisis. What I
felt when I moved into engineering
management over a decade ago. Honestly,
it was the right time for me to step
sideways into a different role. But I
really didn't want to move away from the
code and the tools.
I felt like I'd be losing my touch, my
edge, the thing that I'd spent so long
getting really good at, and that I'd
become rusty if I wasn't tinkering every
day. Instead, I had to learn to lead and
trust my teams to solve the problems and
deliver the outcomes that I'd been used
to doing myself. In many ways, I felt
like I was outsourcing my job and my
satisfaction to others, and it honestly
didn't feel great.
Patrick Dvoir recently wrote about the
four patterns of AI native development
that he's been observing and has
identified. The first one from producer
to manager sounds strikingly familiar to
my shift from software engineering to
engineering management. And he describes
the shift from writing code ourselves to
reviewing and accepting code. How we're
essentially becoming managers of agent
development teams orchestrating and
overseeing the production of code by AI.
Right. So great, but what now? Right. I
honestly don't know. I I wish I had a
crystal ball and I could see how all of
this is going to work out. But I don't.
However, I I do know that we have no
option but to learn how to work in this
new system. So, let's think this
through. We can start by reclaiming some
of that broader role that we often
describe software engineering to
include. If you've specialized on
writing code, I think it would be a good
idea to find opportunities to gain some
experience doing those other tasks like
gathering requirements, designing or
architecting solutions, creating test
strategies, writing automated tests and
evals, building DevOps,
um running, maintaining, debugging them
when they break. You know, these are all
really great skills to have and you
learn best by doing. So find
opportunities to do them. See if you can
be the supply to that neverending unmet
demand. With AI, that specialization
that felt necessary to cope with the
growing demand and complexity of
software engineering may simply not be
there
anymore. Roles that had been split up
among multiple people can be compressed
back into fewer with AI supporting the
gaps. Now, we're already seeing this
play out in many startups where far
fewer people are needed to get an idea
off the ground by leveraging AI. So,
this isn't just theory.
I also know that with new tech come new
tools, new problems and new solutions.
And this is going to require new
builders. So we may not write any every
line of code anymore, but it doesn't
mean that we won't be solving problems
and building things, which at the end of
the day is really what is at the core of
being a software engineer, right? So
let's think about what these new problem
domains that may emerge might be. Prompt
engineering is becoming a new core
skill. Knowing how to frame problems
clearly, guide outputs and shape systems
without writing every line of code
manually. This may even promote prompts
or specs to first class citizens,
meaning we should start storing them
alongside the code that they
generate. This might require smarter
source control systems, which may also
need to cope with an increasing amount
of code that's being generated.
Then there's learning how to build and
run non-deterministic systems and how to
test and debug them. And how to delegate
authority to AI agents that operate on
your behalf without giving them all of
your
credentials. Imagine what an internet
designed for AI might look like where
the traffic is mostly generated by
AIdriven
interactions. And last but not least,
how do we design teams that are made up
of both humans and AI agents? What does
a high performance human AI team even
look like? and how do we measure
collaboration? So, there are lots of new
problems to start thinking about. And if
you're designing and building AI tools
or workflows, consider the importance of
creativity. Creativity is an a really
critical aspect of design of software
design. So, Google researchers have come
up with an idea that they call seamful
AI to support both productivity and
creativity in software development. As
the name implies, rather than making it
a seamless experience, we could
deliberately highlight the scenes
because that's where creativity lives
and where learning happens. So, for
example, as we said earlier, Genai
doesn't signal doubt. But perhaps it
could if it isn't confident in its
answer. It should just tell us. That
simple act of signaling doubt would
allow us to engage our critical
judgment, exercise that calibrated trust
rather than just accepting the first
answer it gives us. And likewise, if
there are multiple possible solutions,
it should just tell us and give us the
opportunity to choose. And to be kind to
our future selves, it could also
document and preserve the options that
weren't selected, capturing the richness
of the decision-making process, not just
the final
output. During the industrial
revolution, crafts people faced a
similar moment. Their hands were no
longer on the tools. Machines had
generally taken over. But most people
didn't just fade away. They became the
ones who designed the factories, fixed
the machines, understood the flows and
optimized systems. And I think that
that's what this moment calls for. We
might not touch every file, but we will
continue to see and understand the
system. So what if awareness becomes
part of the new
craft? When I first became a manager, I
thought I was leaving engineering behind
for good, and it hurt. I didn't want to
let go of that part of me that built
things. But over time, I found my way
back. I've swung from IC to leadership
and back again multiple times and
realized that identity isn't fixed. So
why not find your own pendulum and swing
between the types of work that you enjoy
doing the most? And always remember your
career doesn't have to be a straight
line as long as you are always learning
and growing new
skills. So do I think that software
engineering is dead? No. No I don't. But
it sure ain't going to look like it has
in the past. Our industry has changed
many times over the years, and this
change is a big and meaningful one. But
our roles are not disappearing. Our
roles are being augmented, and we're
evolving in ways that we're only just
starting to figure out. But the great
thing is that nobody really knows our
roles better than we do, what great
software engineering looks and feels
like. So honestly, there's no one better
than us to reimagine what it looks like
in this new age of AI.
So, are you still a software engineer if
you don't write the code yourself?
Honestly, I think there are better
questions to ask like, are you still
solving problems? Are you still shaping
systems and still carrying the craft
forward? If so, then yes, I think you're
still a software engineer, but just a
reimagined one. You don't need to have
it all figured out. Just stay curious.
Keep asking questions and explore this
new landscape. The pendulum will swing
and the tools will continue to change.
But the essence of our craft, solving,
building, and thinking, that's ours to
carry
forward. All right, that's that's all
folks.
Um, thank you for your time and
attention. I hope you enjoyed that.
That was wonderful. It was a truly truly
lovely session and uh very eloquently
delivered as well. So thank you very
very much Annie for a really important
session. Um we we've got a number of uh
of questions here. Um let's take a look.
Uh first of all why don't we start with
a quote. Uh this is this is a really
nice it was a very nice eloquent quote
as well talking about lots of technical
hurdles but those are the sand in our
boots. And I really like that. I really
like that quote. So I kind of want a
lovely way to put it first. Um, so Juan
asks, um, do you recommend doing an
online master's degree in AI, even if
it's asynchronous, which I guess, you
know, alongside alongside work, uh, or
doing is not necessarily at all to work
in this field. I'm planning to join the
master's degree from Texas University.
Um, are you are you in work at the
minute? Are you doing work uh are you in
the trade as it were as as we're as
we're talking? Uh, feel free to feel
free to um go ahead with the question.
Well, well, from my perspective, I I
would say any kind of education,
self-arning, online mast's degrees, or
at a university, I I think it's
worthwhile doing because you're not just
going to learn the material that they
teach you. You're going to learn about
how to learn about the material that
they're teaching you and everything
else, right? You'll meet other people.
It'll it'll send you down paths that you
didn't even know existed. So I I yes I
would absolutely recommend doing an
online mast's degree or just any kind of
learning if AI is a thing that you're
interested in then go for it one and if
you're already in industry do you think
it's do you think it's worth any formal
education in a kind of AI um uh AI
curriculum role or sorry curriculum um
academic degree or something like that
or do you feel like you know a lot of
this can kind of like be built uh on the
role or through courses and things like
that. I think it really depends.
I think it it really depends on the the
the company you work for and the role
that you're in. If you're getting lots
of opportunities at work to experiment
and and learn on the job, learning by
doing is the best way. Absolutely. But
yeah, if you're in a role where perhaps
you you have a lot of day-to-day work to
get on with and it doesn't include much
of the stuff that you don't already
know, then if you if you can stand doing
one and a half jobs or or even two jobs
at the same time because studying starts
to feel like a second job, ask me how I
know this. Um it's worth doing, right?
It it just it expands the mind. So I'
I'd say so. Awesome. Awesome. Cool. Uh
we have um here's a here's a nice
question actually. Uh I've been watching
uh I've been watching training change
over my 30 plus year career having been
a software trainer early on but watching
that need go away as learning advances
from courses books Google stack overflow
and now geni gen AI platforms the
question is how do you see learning
change with AI as a professional in
college what replaces it in high school
what replaces it and there's an
interesting uh question that was asked
to GIO uh who which was um would you if
you were a student now go into a
computer science degree and interesting
oh sorry no it is would you recommend to
your to your child go into the computer
science degree and interestingly he said
no and I think the vast reason there was
because actually an existing computer
science degree doesn't actually
represent the needs or or provide the
needs as to what that likely future AI
role is is going or AI developer role is
going to require um what do you feel
needs to change in terms of our
education our schools to be more uh
adept or equipped for for AI development
Yeah, this is a really great question
and it's actually something that I've
started talking to a few other
professors at universities and and
researchers at Google about and with a
bit of luck we'll be collaborating on a
paper about this later in the year. Um,
look for for some time already I think
there's been some criticism of at least
tertiary education and computer science
that it's not as relevant as it needs to
be for the job. And even when I
graduated over 20 years ago, my first
job, I didn't put to use any of like the
tangible skills that I learned at
university. But I think it helps you
build a foundation that you don't even
realize helps, you know, it it just
helps explain why some of the decisions
you make are good decisions. Even if
like I I learned Java and C++ at
university, and I've never had a job in
either of those. So, it's not about
learning the syntax so much as those
underlying concepts. I mean, I learned
how data was stored on a a hard drive.
I've never been a hardware engineer, but
somehow that that stuck with me and it
helped me understand maybe I shouldn't,
you know, I should put more things in
the cache, so it's not writing to disk
and reading from disk all the time
because it's spinning around so much and
it's it's things like that. But plenty
of people have had very lucrative
careers without having had a huge amount
of, you know, tertiary level education.
And so moving forwards and the more we
move away from the code itself like
yesterday I was watching a YouTube video
and somebody said that they feel like
they no longer need to micromanage their
code.
That's a really interesting way of
putting it because they're not writing
it so much anymore because they're
really leaning into the vibe coding. So
I I think what will the foundations are
probably going to change and maybe some
of the principles that we've always
known to be true maybe some of those
might change as well. So I would say
it's it's still worth you know pursuing
education and in these topics but
educators need to move with the times
and make sure that they are teaching
things that are going to be relevant
moving forward. Yeah. Awesome. Annie, we
have minus 90 seconds left. Uh so
perhaps in 30 seconds let's try and uh
let's try and uh tackle Jean's question.
Jean Kim's question. uh wonderful art.
What what was the biggest surprise in
your analysis of all the responses as
people talked about how their work is
changing with AI?
My biggest surprise, this is a really
great
question. I think I was genuinely
surprised at how many people feel so
strongly about the changes and yet I
hadn't really seen it elsewhere. You
know, all I've seen is a lot of either
positivity around these new tools are
incredible and and I can't wait to lean
into it or these tools are never going
to replace software engineers or or
software engineering cuz you know they
constantly hallucinate. They're always
wrong that and and yet there wasn't much
about how do you feel about that craft
like are you going to miss it? Do you
feel like the next generation of
developers are not going to have quite
the same fun that we did? And there's
50,000 plus people who seem to feel some
form of that. And um yeah, I I hope it
gives people permission to speak a
little more freely about how it makes
them feel. You know, the more we talk
about it, we can do something about it
together. So yeah, a great question.
What a lovely sentiment to end on there
as well. Um yeah, Annie, thanks once
again. Uh lovely session, really
eloquently given and um a lot of uh of
things for folks to to think about there
as well going forward. So, thank you for
Thanks so much for having me.
Absolutely.